Can't sleep and can't get up.
睡不着起不来
What does the resolution mean?
这什么辩题啊
It depends on the situation.
都得视情况而定
Right.
没错
Is it more painful not to be able to sleep at night?
是晚上睡不着更痛苦
Or is it more painful not to be able to get up in the morning?
还是早上起不来更痛苦
Then the two sides can make casual statements.
这不是双方自说自话
There are no criteria for judgement.
没有评判标准了
Gosh!
天呐
I haven't slept
已经四十八个小时
for forty-eight hours.
没睡觉了
I really want to sleep!
好想睡一觉啊
I would like to reply the question of my fellow debater.
回答对方辩友的问题
It's difficult to compare which one is more painful.
哪个更痛苦不好比
How about comparing
我们不妨就比较一下
which one is less painful?
哪个更不痛苦
Then the other one is
那么另一个不
more painful.
就是更痛苦了吗
Then I would like to ask my fellow debater to tell me more.
那请对方辩友指教详情
If you can't get up in the morning,
早上起不来
the alarm clocks
你还有闹钟
and the fear of being late
和迟到的恐惧
will urge you to get up.
督促你起床
But if you can't sleep at night,
但晚上睡不着
there's no way to solve it.
是真的没有办法
You not only can't sleep now,
不仅现在睡不着
but have to worry about
而且早上还要担心
not getting up in the morning.
起不来的情况
Your pains double.
你看 双倍痛苦
Compared with the alarm clock in the morning,
比起早上闹铃
the phone call and being late,
电话 迟到
which are considered as a triple fear,
恐惧三连杀来说
it is less painful.
还没那么痛苦
Won't you be painful if you can't get up?
起不来不痛苦啊
You don't even get up. You are still sleeping.
你都没起来还睡着呢
How could you be in pain?
你痛苦什么呀
Of course, the sober one
当然还是清醒的人
is more painful.
更痛苦了
Congratulations to Team 235
恭喜二三五辩论队
for winning this game.
赢得本场比赛
Congratulations to the opposing side, Team of DUFE
恭喜反方东财大辩论队
Our next rival is
我们的下一个对手
from Poyang College.
鄱阳学院
The team is called "floating in the waves".
江湖人称浪里飘
They are good at interweaving arguments.
擅长交织型立论
Because their arguments seem
因为他们的立论看起来
simple.
很简单
In fact...
实际上呢
In fact,
实际上
the point, line and surface are linked together,
点 线 面连成一片
which can defeat you straight away.
直接把你拍死在沙滩上
The result of the game is now
现在比赛的结果
in my hands.
已经在我的手上
Stop shaking.
别抖了
Congratulations to Team 235
恭喜二三五辩论队
for winning this game.
赢得本场比赛
Congratulations!
让我们恭喜他们
Look.
看
So, the most typical one is
所以最典型的就是
about the trolley.
电车难题
One for all, right?
死一个救一群 对不对
Not really.
不一定
I think
我觉得
the core
现在主要核心
of the discussion now
讨论的观点是
is the democratic system.
民主制度
Western democracy like
像西方那种
one man, one vote
一人一票似的民主
often results in
往往会造成
violence by the majority.
多数人的暴力
Do you agree that this kind of
你能说这种暴力
violence is also just?
也是正义的吗
It depends on the definition
那要看你怎么去定义
of justice.
正义了
As the rule of
如果是从
survival of the fittest in natural selection,
物竞天择的角度来看
it's just.
它就是正义呢
Can I ask my fellow debaters one question?
请问对方辩友
If the violence of the majority
如果多数人的暴力
is conducive to the continuation of human civilization,
有利于人类文明的延续
isn't it just?
那难道不是正义的吗
Do you mean that
您的意思是
injustice to the individual
对个体的不义
can lead to justice for the group?
可以成就群体的正义吗
No. That's not what I meant.
不 我不是这个意思
I think that
我认为
justice changes with the times.
正义是随时代而变化的
So, is there a clear definition of
那么同一时期的正义
justice for the same period?
有明确的定义吗
If there is,
如果有
aren't you making a self-contradicting?
您方不是自相矛盾吗
If there isn't,
如果没有
Then what is the real justice?
那正义何以称为正义呢
The resolution is
辩题是
should campus violence be severely sentenced?
校园暴力该不该重判
My answer is yes.
我觉得应该
Now,
现在
how many children
有多少孩子
are influenced by campus violence?
受校园暴力的影响
But
可这样
isn't this against
不就违背了
the rationality of the law?
法律的理性吗
The law is constantly improved.
法律是不断完善的
If one advocates for a severe sentence,
如果主张重判的话
it means that the sentence is too light now.
意思就是现在太轻了
It's not that rational.
不够理性
You have a point there.
有道理
Actually,
其实啊
this is easily agreed upon
这一点双方很容易
by both sides.
达成共识
But the problem is
但问题是
whether the result of the severe sentence is appropriate.
重判的结果是否恰当
Campus violence cases are on the rise.
校园暴力案件不断增加
The severe sentence can
重判能够起到
play an exemplary role, right?
示范意义 不是吗
Is it right to take the so-called exemplary role
取所谓示范意义
and sacrifice
而舍法律公平公正
the fairness and justice of the law?
是应该的吗
The law allows
法律本身就允许将
to take social values
社会价值考虑
into account when sentencing.
进量刑范畴
My fellow debater's understanding of
对方辩友对法律
the fairness of the law is
的公正性
biased, right?
理解偏颇了吧
Campus violence
校园暴力
is common
普遍发生在
among minors.
未成年人身上
Passionate violence dominates.
激情暴力占据多数
The exemplary role
示范作用
is inherently weaker than that on adults.
本来就弱于成年人
With the continuous development of society,
随着社会的不断发展
the age of mental maturity
青少年心智
of adolescents
成熟的年纪
is advancing.
也不断提前
When adolescents' characters
如果激情暴力
are being formed,
在青少年性格
if passionate violence
养成的时候
becomes habitual violence
变成了习惯性暴力
or even violent values,
甚至暴力价值观
a light sentence for campus violence
轻判校园暴力
will be harmful.
则贻害无穷
Congratulations to Team 235
恭喜二三五辩论队
for winning this game.
赢得本场比赛
The winner is
本次获胜方是
Team 235.
二三五队
Congratulations to them for advancing to the semi-final.
恭喜他们进入四强
Let's go.
走吧
Our game is about to start, too.
我们的比赛也要开始了
This is the end.
到此为止
My argument is complete.
论证完毕
Anonymity has many drawbacks,
匿名有很多的弊端
and many imperfections.
也有很多的不完美
But it guarantees
但是它保证了
the ultimate purpose of the online discussion.
网络讨论中的最终目的
This purpose
这一目的
can only be achieved
也只有在网络讨论中
in a real sense in the online discussion.
才能真正意义地实现
It seems that
看样子
the result will be available soon.
很快就可以出结果了
I didn't expect that
没有想到
we entered the final ahead of them.
我们比他们还先进决赛
This is the gap.
这就是差距
Never mind.
没事
When they finish the game,
等他们比完赛
let's laugh at them.
好好埋汰埋汰他们
Don't worry. Maybe they
别急 说不定他们
won't enter the semi-final.
进不了四强呢
Fie!
呸呸呸
The real-name system looks perfect
实名看上去很美
and civilized.
很文明
But it can't achieve the goal.
但是它达不到这一目的
It fails.
不及格
So, the advantages outweigh the disadvantages.
所以 利大于弊
Thank you.
谢谢
Now,
现在
I announce
我来宣布本场的结果
the winner is
获胜的是
the affirmative side, Dongzhou University of Finance and Economics.
正方 东州财经大学
I don't know if I should be happy
不知道应该高兴
or unhappy.
还是不高兴
It's all right. Be confident in yourself.
没事 对自己有点信心
This is the end of today's game.
今天的比赛到此结束
The teams entering the semi-final
进入半决赛队伍
come in the afternoon
下午来抽取
to decide the next game's resolution and motion.
下一场的题目和持方
Everyone was tired lately.
大家最近 都很辛苦
But,
但是
there will be only two more games for us.
我们就剩两场比赛了
The two times
这时间实在是
are really too close.
挨得太紧了
Don't worry, Hao.
放心吧 小好姐
We still have the awareness
我们这点备赛的意识
of preparation for the game.
还是有的
Okay.
好
Then let's have look at
那我们看一下
the resolution in the semi-final.
接下来半决赛的辩题
Accepting the reality and changing the reality.
接受现实和改变现实
Which one needs more courage?
哪个更需要勇气
Accepting the reality.
接受现实
Why?
为什么
Because if you let me
因为如果让我现在
accept
马上接受
the debate we're going to have right now,
咱们要打的这个辩题
it would take a lot of courage.
就很需要勇气
I think that to accept that we are
我觉得接受我们是
the passive party
被动的一方
takes more courage.
更需要勇气
Our motion is
我们的持方是
to accept the reality needs more courage.
接受现实更需要勇气
It's all over.
完蛋
It's difficult.
难搞
But we still need to get it even if it is difficult.
不过再难搞也得搞
So, it's even
所以我们
more important
更加要好好开始
to start preparing for the debate.
准备辩题了
I hope
希望
there's no more
不要再有戏剧性的
drama.
事情发生
Extra! Extra!
号外号外 惊天号外
I tell you.
我跟你们说
Do you know who is
你们知道我们下一场
our next rivalry?
对手是谁吗
Nanjiang Drama Academy
南戏学院
Do you know
那你们知道
who is their leader?
他们的领队是谁吗
Please draw the motion.
请抽取持方
Hello. You can start.
二位 可以开始了
Senior
师哥
It's been a long time.
好久不见
No wonder Sa was
我说小撒这几天
so distracted these days,
怎么这么魂不守舍的
and disappeared suddenly.
还总玩失踪
It seemed that he went to meet that girl.
看来是找妹子去了
What does she look like?
长什么样啊
Right.
对
Anyway, to be with Sa,
反正配小撒
she is aggrieved.
我觉得委屈了
Is she tall?
高不高
She's tall.
高
Her skin is fair.
皮肤特白
Is she fair-skinned?
白吗
Fairly white.
老白呗
So, there's a reason
所以现在
why the price of crude oil
原油价格降不下来
can't come down now.
是有原因的
Right.
对
Yes.
是
Right?
是吧
Sa
小撒
Uh?
嗯
Who is our rivalry in the next game?
咱们下场比赛打谁呀
Nanjiang Drama Academy.
南戏呀
It's the first time for us to play the provincial tournament.
咱们都是第一次打省赛
We are not particularly
就对对手也不是
knowledgeable about the rivalry, either.
特别了解
Right.
嗯
Do you know about Nanjiang Drama Academy?
你了解南戏吗
I, I mean...
我 我是说
It's been so many years since graduation.
毕业都这么多年了
I don't know about the present Nanjiang Drama Academy.
现在的南戏我不了解
But as for the Nanjiang Drama Academy six or five years ago,
但要说 五六年前的吧
I don't know well about it.
也不太了解
All right!
好了好了
Let's
那大家
continue to discuss the resolution.
再继续讨论辩题吧
Can we rely on Dandan?
蛋蛋行不行啊
Does he forget the mission
他不会是忘了任务
and have a date?
真去约会了吧
It's all right.
没事
Even if he's dating,
就算是约会
he does that for Mr. Sa.
那也是为了小撒老师
Well.
哎
What is that crap?
这叫什么事
What's going on?
怎么样
Come on.
你快点
I have a friend's
我以前有一朋友的
girlfriend
女朋友
who was from Jiangnan Drama Academy.
那是江南戏剧学院的
Her future boyfriend's
她未来男朋友的
confidant
红颜知己呢
is a member of the school debate.
正是学校辩论队的
We used
我俩就以
the comic, One Piece
一个海贼王漫画
as a token of love.
作为定情信物
No, no, no. Watchword.
不不不 接头暗号
We met each other
在一个巷子里的
at a lamb spine hot pot restaurant
羊蝎子馆
in an alley.
接上头了
When she saw me,
她一见到我
her mouth was nearly watering.
那哈喇子都流出来了
Tell us the point.
重点 说重点
The point is that
重点就是
the name of that girl is Diandian.
那姑娘叫典典
She is a schoolmate of Sa at college...
和小撒是大学同学
There are photos of them
她手机里还有
on her phone.
两个人的合影呢
What else?
然后呢
That's all.
没了
Right.
啊
Aren't there some stories?
没点历史故事啥的
Her teammates don't know about that.
人队员也不知道
They know as much as you do.
和你们一样
Then you went there for a long time,
那你去了半天
what did you study?
你研究什么去了
If you want to know about
你如果想知道
the confidant,
那红颜知己的消息呢
I even know
我倒是连他们小区
how many stray cats there are
有多少只流浪猫
in their neighborhood.
都一清二楚
Accepting the reality needs more courage.
接受现实更需要勇气
What's the main logic?
主体逻辑是什么
The main logic is that
逻辑主体就是
the reality will be more miserable.
现实会更惨
Why?
为什么
If it's not miserable, why do you need courage?
不惨你需要什么勇气呀
If we all live in the
要是咱们都生活在
the Disney fairy tale,
迪士尼童话故事里面
we need nothing.
我也什么都不需要
So, we now
所以咱们现在
agree that
同意这个辩题的
the implicit premise of
隐性前提
this debate
就是面对不愉快的现实
is whether we should accept
我们到底是接受
or change the unpleasant reality in the face of it.
它还是改变它
Is that right?
对吧
Right. Our motion is that
对 我们的持方是
accepting the reality needs more courage.
接受现实更需要勇气
Indeed. If we're faced with
确实 如果面对一个
an unpleasant decision,
令人不怎么愉快的决定
but we have to accept,
但是我们却要接受它
it is quite courageous.
是挺需要勇气的
Right.
没错
When we are faced with
我们在面临
an unsatisfactory reality,
不遂人意的现实的时候
our first reaction is to change it.
第一反应就是要改变它
To overcome this impulse,
要克服这种冲动
and to try accepting it
还要尝试去接受它
are really quite difficult.
确实挺难的
In my opinion,
要我说啊
to try accepting it
我也觉得尝试改变
is easier.
比较容易一点
For example, when I once committed a mistake,
就像我当初犯错
I borrowed money from everyone.
到处乱借钱
My first reaction is
我第一反应就是
to try to
想怎么把这件事
cover the mistake.
给糊弄过去
Because the reality
因为现实
is too frightening.
太可怕了
Everyone agrees that we are
大家都同意我们这次
the advantageous side this time, right?
算是优势方了
I don't think so.
我不觉得
The reality is harsh.
现实它很残酷
It's difficult to change it.
想要改变它很难
When people
人呢
are faced with a more difficult
在面对更难
problem,
的问题的时候
they need more courage.
才更需要勇气
I don't think so.
我觉得不是
Accepting a hard reality
接受一个难受的现实
is obviously more difficult.
显然更困难
If the reality doesn't
要是现实没有达到
meet your expectations,
你的预期
then let's go to
那我们就去
beat it up.
干翻它
When you have been ravaged by reality
等你被现实蹂躏了
a hundred times,
一百次
you will feel that
你就会觉得
it is easier to accept it.
接受它比较简单
You continue the discussion.
你们先聊
I'm going to
我去
clean the car.
擦个车
One hundred...
一百
You deserted me,
你居然抛下了我
our debate team,
抛下了我们的辩论队
and our dream
抛下了我们三年
for three years.
以来的梦想
Have we promised
不是说好了
to be teammates
要做彼此
of each other forever?
一辈子的队友吗
Diandian
典典
Please forgive me.
请你原谅我
I have to go back to my hometown.
我要回到我的故乡
Like an ostrich,
像一只鸵鸟一样
forget everything.
忘掉了这一切
No. I don't want to forget that.
不 我不要忘记
Let me stay
让我带着我们的梦想
with our dream.
留下来
I will take our school team
我要带着我们的校队
to the provincial tournament.
打进省赛
No.
不
It's not worth it for my sake.
为了我不值得
I will wait.
我要等
I will be here
我一直在这儿
to wait for you.
等着你
Many years later...
多年后
Diandian
典典
You are really waiting for me.
你真的在等着我
The heat is killing me.
热死我了
How's it?
怎么样
When Sa comes here later,
一会儿小撒来了
we are going to
我们两个就打算这么
show him this.
表演给他看
We hope it will encourage him.
希望能够激励他
I think it is
我觉得你们真的
a good show.
演得很好
But I am a little worried that
但我就是有点担心
Sa will
小撒看了之后
thinks that
会不会觉得
you are satirizing him.
是在讽刺他呀
How can that happen?
怎么可能
We are so sincere.
我们两个多真诚啊
Right? We are sincere.
是不是 特别走心
Hey.
诶
Do you think
你们说
Sa is a slag man
小撒当年就这么走了
because he left ruthlessly?
算不算渣男啊
I don't think so.
怎么可能啊 不算
They all had a special emotion
他们两个当时对彼此
with each other.
都有好感
What's more,
更何况
they were not
人俩人根本就
in a relationship.
不是男女朋友
The emotion which is more intimate than friendship, but less than love is the most difficult situation.
恋人未满最难搞
Sa
小撒当年
must have had no choice
肯定也是迫不得已
but to return here that year.
才回到这儿的
They lived in different places.
人俩可算异地呀 这样
What pitiful lovers!
也是可怜的一对
Wait.
等等
Our three pairs of lovers will be in different places
我们三对
after graduation.
毕了业也是异地
The long-distance relationship
异地恋啊
ranks the top one
那毕业分手
on the list of breaking up after graduation.
排行榜第一名
It's okay.
没关系
Where Xiaoyu is going to in the future,
以后小鱼去哪儿啊
I will go there as well.
我就去哪儿
Anyway, I am a talent.
反正像我这样的人才
No matter where I am,
不论放在哪里
I will have a bright future like a leaping monkey.
蹿天猴一样
A leaping monkey.
蹿天猴
I have negotiated with Ma Nan.
我跟马楠也约好了
We will stay at the same place
以后我跟他一起
to make our mortgage payments.
房贷一起还
You have already planned.
你们都规划好了
But I...
可是我
I will also
我也要跟
go with Yanze.
着我们家小彦彦一起走
I will go where he goes.
他去哪儿我去哪儿
Ma Nan, what are you looking at?
马楠 你在这儿看什么呢
Sa
小撒
You are perverted to have this fetish.
你好变态 有这癖好啊
You don't stare at juniors.
学校的学妹你不看
You stare at the middle-aged man.
看这中年男子
He is dating with
他在跟那个叫
the girl who is called Diandian.
典典的姑娘约会
What?
什么什么什么
Really?
真的假的
Senior
师哥
How have you been all these years?
这些年 还好吗
Just so-so.
还凑合
I just didn't expect to
就是没想到在
see you here.
这儿能见到你
I feel happy.
挺开心的
I'm not surprised.
我一点都不意外
Since you played the points race
你们作为二队打
as the team two,
积分赛的时候
I've been following you guys.
我就已经关注着了
Although you were not
虽然那时候你们境遇
in a good situation at that time,
并不太好
I believe
但是我相信
we will meet
我们一定能在
in the provincial tournament.
省赛遇到的
Diandian
典典
Actually,
其 其实
we almost failed several times.
有好几次也挺悬的
The team you lead
你带的队伍
must be fine.
一定没问题
Diandian
典典
You...
你
How have you been
你 你这些年
all these years?
过得怎么样
Not bad.
还不错呀
After you left,
你走之后
I led the debate team
我就带着辩论队
to enter the provincial tournament.
进了省赛
Although we stopped at the last eight,
虽然止步八强
the grade of us was not bad.
但成绩还算不错
Then I started to take part in the entrance exams for postgraduate schools.
然后我就着手考研了
I didn't think
没想到
it would be easy
考本校研究生
to get into our school as a postgraduate.
还挺容易的
So, I still had time
所以我还有时间
to train the debate team.
一边操持着辩论队
Then the debate team did not do well.
后来辩论队成绩平平
When I was in my second year as a postgraduate,
直到我研二的时候
I met two excellent juniors.
遇到了两个厉害的学弟
The debate team once again entered the provincial tournament.
再一次杀进省赛
How do you feel?
怎么样
Am I completing
是不是比你先完成
our team's ambition before you?
我们队的宏愿啊
You are better than me.
还是你厉害
Do you still
这以前的事
remember the past?
你都还记得呀
Of course.
当然啊
You were saying 800 times a day
你当时一天要说八百遍
to advance to the provincial tournament.
挺进省赛
How could I ever forget that?
我怎么可能忘得掉
Well.
那
Did you do that
是 是为了
for me?
我吗
What are you thinking about?
你想什么呢
I always want to stay in Shanghai.
我是一直想留在上海
As for me,
对我而言
the simplest way is to be a postgraduate
最简单的办法就是考研
of our school and work in our school.
留校啊
Besides,
而且
debating is my strength.
打辩论可是我的强项
Our school is now paying special attention to me.
学校现在可倚重我呢
Okay.
哦
Well.
那
Pretty good.
挺好的
Right.
嗯
It's pretty good.
是挺好的
But what is much better is that
不过更好的是
you become
你还是当上了
a coach of the debate team again.
辩论队教练
Nope.
哎
I am just an agent coach.
我是代理的
My professor is the real one.
我的教授才是教练
But you do it well.
不过你真是超厉害
I heard from the staff
我这两天听工作人员说
that you are already
你已经是非常
an excellent devil coach.
出色的魔鬼教练
Slander.
诽谤
Do you think that I am an evil coach?
你觉得我像魔鬼吗
Of course not.
当然不是
In my mind,
你在我心里
you are always a little girl.
一直是个小女孩
You don't think
你该不会以为
I'm staying for you,
我是为了你
do you?
才留下来的吧
Of course not.
当然 当然 当然不是
That's right.
没错
I'm staying for you.
就是为了你
Why do you know
你怎么知道他们在
what they are talking about?
说什么
I can read lips.
我会读唇语
Why don't you tell us earlier?
怎么不早说
What did they talk about?
他 他俩刚刚说什么
Well.
这个嘛
Actually, the thing is...
其实就是这样
Those who hear it are sad.
就是闻者伤心
Those who hear it are tearful.
听者流泪
It's heroic and moving.
可歌可泣
Heroic and moving.
可歌可泣呀
Really.
真的
Come on.
快说
Okay. Okay.
说说 我说我说我说
How can this be?
这怎么能这样呢
What does Sa think about?
那小撒想什么呢
Diandian must be waiting for him.
典典姐肯定是在等他呢
I agree.
我同意
I've seen the payroll
我可是看过小撒
of Sa.
工资条的人
With Diandian's good look and talent,
以典典姐的长相和才华
being a counselor is unworthy.
当个辅导员太屈才了
I agree.
我也同意
Diandian has been
典典姐一直
thinking of helping Sa to complete his dream.
想着帮小撒完成梦想
In the end,
坚持到最后
it became her own dream.
变成自己的梦想了
We are clear-headed because we are bystanders.
我们是旁观者清
We do not know
就是不知道
if Diandian knows
典典知不知道
Sa's emotion.
小撒的心意啊
Hey! What's up?
哟 怎么了
Why are you here?
你怎么在这儿啊
The same as you.
跟你一样
Comics?
看漫画
Right.
对呀
Everyone is preparing for the semi-final.
大家都在准备半决赛
You are here reading comics.
你在这里看漫画
Aren't you frightened that Hao will scold at you?
你不怕小好骂你吗
I am preparing for the race.
我就是在准备比赛
Otherwise,
要不然你以为
where do you think
我结辩里边
I got those life lessons and examples
那些人生感悟和案例
in my closing arguments?
是从哪儿来的
From comics?
漫画啊
Right.
对呀
Look.
你看这个
What?
什么
Naruto.
火影忍者
Do you know why
知道为什么
Sakura finally succeeded being with Sasuke
这么多人喜欢佐助
when so many people
但最后只有
love Sasuke?
小樱追到了吗
I don't know.
不知道
Because she is persistent.
因为她坚持不懈
Listen to me.
你看
There are many girls
有那么多女生对
having crush on Sasuke.
佐助流哈喇子
But,
但是呢
they all have secrets or problems they don't want to reveal.
她们都有难言之隐
They dare not to show their love.
都不敢说
Only Sakura dares to show her love.
只有小樱敢表白
And she keeps showing her love.
而且是那种不断地表白
But she was rejected over and over again.
又不断地拒绝
Finally, she doesn't care whether she will be loved.
最终没人要了也无所谓
Sakura
那这个小樱
really loves
她确实喜欢
Sasuke.
这个叫佐助的
Is it him?
他吗
Look. He's handsome.
你看这 很帅嘛
The young version of me.
很有我年轻时候的姿色
But,
但是你看啊
Sakura has the body of a woman
小樱她头脑简单
and the mind of a child.
四肢发达
She's incapable of dealing with matters.
做事能力也差
She also knows that
她自己也知道
she is worse than others at many aspects.
样样都不如人家
But why is she so persistent?
她为什么还这么执着呢
Why?
为什么
Because
因为啊
she knows that
她自己心里也清楚
she won't encounter a better one.
她遇不到更好的了
Do you get it?
知道吧
She is so realistic.
这么现实
At the age of 30 years old,
三十啷当岁
isn't it good to be realistic?
现实一点不挺好的吗
It makes sense.
有道理
I tell you.
我跟你说
Actually, Sasuke also knows that
其实佐助心里也明白
he owns a lot to Sakura,
他一直欠小樱的
and he feels sorry for Sakura.
一直对不起小樱
But it doesn't matter.
但是 都没关系
After they are together with each other,
他们两个在一块
everything will be paid back.
慢慢会偿还的
What's more,
再说了
it's hard to say
最后谁占谁便宜
who is more advantageous.
还不知道呢
You mean me?
你是在说我吗
I said I was working on the debate.
我说了我在弄辩题
Bro
大哥
Do you know that?
你知道吗
Sometimes it's really difficult
有的时候改变现实
to change the reality.
真的很难
It's much more difficult than what you imagine.
比你想象中还要难
I didn't even know
我当时都不知道
what I could do
我如果留下来
if I stayed.
我能干些什么
If you have another chance
那如果再给你一个机会
will you stay?
你会留下来吗
Of course.
会啊
There is no more chance.
这不是没有机会了吗
You are so anxious.
你说你这么纠结
Are you afraid to face the reality
到底是害怕面对现实
or afraid to face
还是害怕面对
the past of your own behavior?
过去自己那些行为啊
I think
我觉得吧
accepting the reality is more difficult than solving it.
接受比解决更要难
So,
所以
why do you put yourself in an awkward situation?
你为什么要为难自己呢
You can choose
你完全可以选一个
a simpler way
更简单的方式
to solve it, right?
你去解决它 对吧
This is a good point.
这是个好点子
I will write it down.
我要记下来
Does this book
那个 这本书里面
tell
讲的就是
the story of the two of them?
他们俩的故事吗
I don't know. I have not finished reading it.
我不知道 我没看完呢
What I said just now was what I guess.
刚才说的都是我推测的
Senior
师哥
Well.
哎
It's so late.
这么晚了
What do you want from me?
找我什么事啊
I just passed by a bookstore
刚才我路过书店
and saw this comic updated.
看见这本漫画更新了
I remember you like it.
我记得你很喜欢
So, I bring it to you on the way.
就顺路给你带过来
Do you still remember that?
你还记着呢
Uh-huh!
啊
I just read some pages.
那个我刚才翻了一下
Sakura and Sasuke
小樱佐助这两个人
are interesting.
挺有意思
You are right.
对啊
I will tell you if there's a chance later.
以后有机会 讲给你听
Do you come here
你特地过来一趟
to give me the comic?
就是给我送漫画
No.
不 不
I just
我 我就是
come here to give you the comic.
来给你送漫画
Thank you.
那谢谢了
You are welcome.
不客气
I got to go.
那我先走了
Be careful.
慢走
Okay.
哎
Diandian, I'm sorry.
典典 对不起
I went back hometown after graduation then.
当时 毕了业我就回家了
You were left in Shanghai alone.
留你一个人在上海
Actually, I was worried about you.
其实我很担心你
But I dared not to contact with you.
但是一直不敢联系你
Because I don't know
因为我不知道应该
how to face you.
怎么面对你
At first, I thought that you would
开始我以为你毕了业
be back hometown after graduation.
也会回家
But from a friend,
可是后来托朋友
I knew that
打听才知道
you had worked at school.
你留校了
I did not think that
我没有想到
my aggressive words at youth
我年轻气盛的一句话
would make you pay for it
会让你为之付出
for so many years.
了这么多年
I owe you an apology.
我欠你一句道歉
I'm sorry.
对不起
You're still asking about me, right?
你还打听着我的消息呢
Right.
啊
I'm always asking about you.
一直打听来着
Ah!
哎呀
It's not for you.
不关你事了
Although it was you
虽然 打进省赛
who said we must enter the provincial tournament,
那句话是你说的
that was my dream as well.
但是那也是我的梦想
I stay here for myself.
我是为了自己留下来的
Besides,
而且
I did what
我做到了学长
you didn't do.
你没做到的事
I'm so proud.
我还挺得意的
Then I'm relieved
那 那知道你过得挺好
to know that you're having a happy life.
我就放心了
Is it enough to be relieved?
放心 就够了
No. Not enough.
不 不够
Not enough?
不够吧
Except that you are sorry,
除了对不起
You have nothing else
你就没有
to say to me, right?
其他的话要和我说了
I have.
有
I have a lot of words to say to you.
有很多
Which aspect do you mean?
你指哪方面
For example,
比如
I miss you as well.
我也很想你
I keep missing you.
一直想你
When I see others debating,
一看到有人打辩论
I would think about you.
我就想你
Well.
那个 这个
It's too late.
时间也挺晚的了
There's a game tomorrow.
明天还要打比赛
How about
要不然
having a rest early?
早 早点休息
Okay.
行
Well.
那
Good night.
晚安
After the game,
要不等打完比赛
I will take you for a good stroll, okay?
我带你好好逛逛
Okay.
好
Good night.
晚安
What's the matter?
怎么了
What were you doing
你们昨天晚上经历了
last night?
些什么
Sa
小撒
You are here.
你来了
Hao, what are you going to do?
小好 你要干什么呀
As for the resolution,
辩题
we can't figure it out.
实在是想不出来了
You scared me!
吓死我了
I thought you were playing
我以为你们这儿演
a ghost movie here.
鬼片呢
Okay, tell me.
那好吧 跟我说说
How's the preparation going?
准备得怎么样了
We have thought for a night.
想了一晚上
Nothing at all.
什么都没有想出来
Why are you so active today?
你今天怎么这么积极呀
Do you have something with Diandian?
你跟典典姐有进展啦
No.
没有
Really?
嗯
Yes.
啊
Bastard.
禽兽
Well.
不
I won't
我以后再也
make her so sad later.
不会让她这么伤心了
I mean
我是说
We worked day and night
我们这么日夜不休地
to prepare for the game.
准备比赛
But you
而你
you are in love.
却在谈恋爱
Is it your own wishful thinking?
是你一厢情愿呢
Or does Diandian
还是典典姐对你
revive the former affection for you?
也旧情复燃呢
Of course...
那当然
It should be the latter one.
应该是后者吧
Did Diandian tell you that?
典典姐说的
I guess.
我猜的
Really?
嗯
Look. Hot pot.
看 火锅
Goodbye.
再见
If slapping on the head is a sign of love,
拍脑门就算示好了
Xiaoyu has loved me
那小鱼打第一天
since the first day
认识我的时候
she met me.
就已经爱死我了
Hey!
哎
Sa
小撒
It's good to be innocent.
单纯是好事
But at the age of over 30 years old,
但你这三十多岁了
it's shameful
又单身又单纯
to be single and innocent.
真挺丢人的
What do you think?
那你们说怎么办呢
It depends on yourself.
看你自己啊
Do you want to be in love with her again?
你是想重新追回她
Or do you want to
还是等比赛结束
let her take her luggage alone,
她一个人拿着行李
and embark on a lonely train
踏上寂寞的火车
to Shanghai which is in the cold winter after the game?
前往寒冬的上海
Then you will never see each other forever.
然后此生不复相见
I have to choose the former one.
那我得选前者吧
That's a good choice.
这就对了嘛
Don't worry. We will help you.
放心吧 我们帮你
Does Diandian have a boyfriend?
典典姐有男朋友吗
Perhaps no.
应该 没有吧
You even don't know about that.
这你都不知道
Give me your phone. Let me check.
手机拿来 我帮你看一下
Debate game, library and comic store.
辩论赛 图书馆 漫画店
It seems that she doesn't have one.
好像还真的没有啊
She doesn't have a boyfriend.
没男朋友
How do you know that?
你怎么知道
I have asked their teammates.
我问了他们队队友
Then hurry up to date with Diandian.
那赶快去约典典姐呀
Hao
小好姐
Why are you so gossipy now?
你现在怎么这么八卦呀
In accordance with your character,
按照你的性格
you should say that like this.
你不是应该说
Alright!
好了好了
They will deal with
人家自己感情的事情
their own affections.
自己解决了
We shouldn't intervene.
我们就不要插手了
Anyway, we have intervened a lot.
反正 都管那么多闲事了
It doesn't matter now.
不差这么一件
Do you want to have dinner together?
一起吃晚饭吗
Well. Why do you all look like
不是 你们怎么都跟
you're gonna give a birth?
要生娃一样
Why are you nervous?
紧张什么呀
But I have to
可是我今天晚上
teach tonight.
要教学生
How about
要不然
ordering take outs and having dinner at the hotel?
我们点外卖在酒店吃
Having dinner at the hotel.
在酒店吃
Wow!
哎哟
Oh, my god!
我的天
I noticed that
我发现你说话
you spoke with a big breath.
怎么大喘气
Do you practice the vital capacity?
练肺活量啊
I don't know whether
就是不知道她这个
her taste changes.
口味变了没有啊
Don't worry.
放心吧
We got omnipotent Shui.
我们有万能的水哥
Here are what you want.
你要的都在这儿
Please enjoy!
敬请享用
Goodbye.
再见
It's easy to break the point.
这个点太容易破了
Change it.
换掉
I got it.
知道了
The refutation is not incisive.
质询不够犀利
It is easy for the other side to master the rhythm.
很容易被对方抢去节奏
Improve it this night.
通宵再改一下
Continue.
接着来
Okay, Ms. Dian.
好的 教练
This is the result of
这就是你们准备了
the preparation all day, right?
一天的结果
Did you enter the previous games
之前的比赛
by luck?
都是凭运气进的吗
Am I interrupting you?
我是不是打扰你们了
No.
没有没有
How about waiting for me for a while?
要不你等我一会儿
I help them to check the materials.
我帮他们看好资料
Okay, I...
好 那我
Diandian
典典姐
We are not in a hurry.
我们不着急
I'm a little hungry.
我有点饿了
Is there anyone wanting to have dinner?
有谁要吃东西吗
I, I, I.
我我我
Let's go.
走
Diandian, see you later.
那典典姐 你们忙
They are so scared of you!
他们好怕你呀
Am I mean?
我很凶吗
Of course not.
不凶不凶不凶
You are definitely not mean.
你当然不凶
Well.
那个
I don't know if your tastes
也不知道你的口味
have changed.
变了没有
No. Nothing changed.
没变 都没变
Come on.
来来来
We used to spend all night
我们以前也像现在这样
in the training room
在训练教室里
preparing for the race like now.
通宵准备比赛
Yes.
是
When I'm watching them
我现在看着他们上场
play,
打比赛
I feel as if
我就感觉我自己
I'm back to school, too.
好像也回学校了似的
After the provincial tournament,
等省赛结束
let's go back to school.
一块回学校看看吧
Good idea.
好啊
I have not been back for a long time.
我都好久没回去了
It seems to be our first time
这好像是我们第一次当
as rivals.
对手
My fellow debaters,
那对方辩友
you have to try your best.
你们得加油啊
We are great.
我们队很强的
There will be no mercy.
是不会手下留情的
How about showing us a little mercy.
那要不然 还是留点
Well, are you afraid?
怎么 怕了
I'm afraid.
怕
Here.
来
It's too greasy. You should eat more.
太腻了 你多吃点
You are still particular about food.
你怎么还这么挑食啊
How skinny you are now!
你看你瘦的
Under high pressure of the tournament,
现在比赛压力大
you'd better eat more.
你得多吃点
You are strong. You need to eat more.
你块头大 你多吃点
Well. I will eat more.
那 那我多吃点
I got to go.
那我先走了
Be careful!
路上小心
Well. Do you have arrangements tomorrow?
那个 明天你什么安排
We will compete with each other tomorrow.
明天我们两队比赛呀
Right.
哦对哦
What will you do after the game?
那 那比完赛呢
After the game,
比完赛
I will take a plane to be back to Shanghai.
我要赶飞机回上海
What a hurry!
这么着急啊
I promised to take you
不是说好带你好好
for a good stroll.
逛逛吗
Do you have something urgent?
有什么急事吗
I need to get back in time for my visa.
我要赶着回去办签证
Next month,
我下个月
I will go to Canada.
就要去加拿大了
Well.
哦 哦
Okay.
这样啊
Have a good journey!
一路平安
Try your best tomorrow.
明天加油
So do you.
你也是
Sa
小撒
You and Diandian...
你跟典典姐
I got a bottleneck.
瓶颈了 瓶颈了 瓶颈了
Listen.
你看啊
The other side has a particularly important
对方有一个特别重要的
argument.
论点
There is a part of reality
有一部分现实
which is impossible
就是明知道不可能
to achieve.
实现的那种
When you are faced with the reality,
面对这部分现实
you still need to change it.
仍然需要改变它
Then there is a kind of desperation and sadness
就有一种 明知不可为
that you know you can't do it, but you have to do it.
而要为之的绝望和悲壮
Do you think that
你说
it needs more courage
这是不是比接受它
than accepting it?
更需要勇气啊
At that time,
想当年呐
when I decided to leave Diandian,
我决定离开典典的时候
it was the toughest time for me.
是我最纠结的时候
I was thinking about the question all the time.
我一直在思考这个问题
But that's the reality.
可现实就是那样
I was hopeless.
我真的很无力
You're really leaving.
你真的要走
Senior, we have entered the provincial tournament.
学长 现在已经进省赛了
Isn't it your dream?
这不是你的梦想吗
If you really want to go,
如果真的要走的话
let's finish the game together.
一起打完比赛
Okay?
可以吗
Diandian
典典
I really want to stay here.
我很想留下来
But,
可是
the company has notified me
工作那边已经通知我
to start working.
入职了
After all, we have to
毕竟我们还是要
face the life.
面对生活的嘛
Why?
为什么
I'm sorry, Diandian.
对不起 典典
I should have
我本该
faced it together with her.
和她一起面对的
So, how do you define the reality?
所以你怎么界定现实呢
How to define the reality?
怎么给现实定义呢
The objectively existing reality.
客观存在的现实
The unchangeable status quo.
不可改变的现状
It's
人呐
difficult for people
很难
to really see the complete reality.
真正看到完整的现实
Most of the time,
多数时候
it's just the reality
只是我们
what we think.
以为的现实罢了
To conclude,
说到底
we are too weak.
就是我们自己太弱小了
A good argument.
好论点
Sa
小撒
Since the argument is so good,
既然论点这么好
let's discuss the resolution.
我们就着这个论点
on this argument.
讨论一下辩题吧
Right. Don't worry about me.
对 对对 不用管我
I'm an adult.
我是个成年人了
I can be responsible for my decision.
我能为自己的决定负责
Go ahead. Prepare for it.
去吧 准备
At that time,
想当年呐
I spent countless nights
我跟典典
like this
也是这样度过了
with Diandian.
无数个通宵
At that time,
想当年
we supported each other like this.
我们也是这样相互扶持
We are discussing the resolution.
我们在讨论辩题呢
Let's take a photo.
拍个照 拍个照
At that time,
想当年呐
We took selfies like this.
我们也是这样的自拍
At that time...
想当年
I have a melatonin tablet here.
那个我这儿有片褪黑素
How about taking it and
要不然你吃了
going back home to have a sleep?
回家睡觉吧
Why do you take it?
你吃那玩意儿干嘛
Do you have a bad sleep?
你睡眠不好吗
I can't write my closing argument.
我结辩写不出来
Well.
哎
Let me do that.
我来吧
You can't be lenient
你不能因为是
because of Diandian.
典典姐就放水啊
At that time,
想当年
I was the Best Debater of Nanjiang Drama Academy.
我也是南戏的最佳辩手
Golden Speaker Four
黄金四辩
It seems that there is a reason
看来南戏一直没有声响
why Nanjiang Drama Academy has not been famous.
是有原因的